software engineering radio episode 54
interview with Frank Bushman
welcome to a new episode on software
engineering radio this time we have an
interview with Frank Bushman on the
microphone is Michael Frank your name is
associated with patterns close to ear
say or better gyro plop and of course
the poses here is where pose our stands
for pattern oriented software
architecture which is a book series by
Wiley why don't you introduce yourself
and that my name is Frank Bushman I'm 46
years old
and I've been in the domain of software
development and software architecture
since more than it's about 30 years now
I studied computing computer science in
Dortmund and learned about objects in
1983 learning similar 67 and started my
professional career in 1990 at Siemens
corporate technology where I'm still
with that unit today since then I worked
in the field of software development
software architecture with a specific
focus on technologies like frameworks
product lines patterns components and
services so well you roots what is
basically the concept or the
technologies that that impress a pure
career at the end I think it was
patterns and why I came into patterns
was a very simple thing when I started
my work at Siemens as a consultant in
projects I realized quickly that I'm
rediscovering things again and again so
reinventing the wheel in each project I
was on and I thought myself hey you are
lazy guy so you can document your
knowledge your design knowledge in that
case so that you have it readily
available on new projects or
that I could be a little more lazier
that was the first idea of my patent
work and that was in 1992 and soon I
discovered that other people were on
that theme as well like the Gang of Four
like Bruce Anderson like Jim Killeen or
Grady Booch and from there it went on
and became what it is today so that is
probably my predominant technology and
the other topic that influenced me very
much because it allowed me access to the
international community was my work on
the C++ standards committee where I met
people like be honest true Stroup and in
that context also Kristin I got the
inventor of similar 67 both of both
persons were my mentors introduced me to
other people so how was it like at those
days how was it different from today we
simply had a little more time to think
about and reflect about things than
today today everything is time to market
driven technology hypes are coming and
going more quickly than they were in the
past we simply had more time to
elaborate a technology proof its
visibility and transfer it into
production or productive software
development today everything must both
go quicker and quicker innovation cycles
became shorter and shorter so the focus
is on something that that works out of
the box quickly and since no technology
actually can fulfill this expectation
more and more technologies I invented
that is my impression the wheel is
turning much much faster today so how
was it basically at the time when goth
was written and poser one was written
were you in contact with Gang of Four
yes yes there was a kind of competition
between the two teams when we learned
and that the Gang of Four was working on
on their book we also started
working on poser one that was in 1993
and interestingly enough there was a big
overlap of the patterns so in poser one
in the original manuscript of the book a
whole lot sets of patterns that is now
published in the Gang of Four book was
also present she's a good thing because
it was a proof that these design ideas
are really patterns but we lost let's
say the competition they published
earlier so we kicked out all of the
patterns that the Gang of Four published
with two exceptions where we described
different variants when golf was
published in 1995 in 1994 and we had our
draft ready in 1995 and was planned
published in 96 yes due to some
production problems I remembered there
there is this aboard you have the child
award so how did that come I have no
clue that was a big surprised neither us
nor Wiley nominated this book as a
candidate for this award so it was a
complete surprise for us and I don't
know who the nominator actually was
nevertheless we won that wart and that
we I still have this the prize which is
a can of adult coke on my desk so what
is this award exactly about does it
still exist today it still exists today
and it Ward's outstanding works in
various disciplines of software such as
books and projects and things what are
you doing in your daily work and how do
patterns influence your your daily work
in my daily work I am working on
concrete projects doing architecture
coaching and also mentoring software
architects I take them by hand and show
them the issues they need to address
parents play an important role when I do
concrete stuff on
I'm not only do coaching but for some
topics that are hard to resolve where
the project has not the right people on
I also do design and in this work pants
play an important role they allow me to
dress things to the point and they also
allow me to enter or to learn about
technical domains I'm not the big expert
in to get in foot into the door so I
read all the pattern books that I can
get to learn about the concepts of
course there are good books and bad
books and I have to distinguish
carefully between things I can use in my
daily work and things I should better
not use but nevertheless they helped me
doing my daily job there's also the
conference we mentioned Europe lop and
at the SE Radio we actually had some
episodes that we recorded at that
conference for example the interview
with James Nobel I guess you were the
one who started the Europe lop series
right that was in 1996 there we had the
first European conference on pattern
languages program design this is the
official name and it was motivated by
the u.s. prop conference I had the luck
to attend the very first plot conference
in Monticello Illinois which is a remote
place in the middle of nowhere and I
actually enjoyed this remoteness is
which read character of the conference
where just 40 people met to discuss
things without being disturbed and
interrupted by daily work by phoned by
email at that time Monticello had one
phone for all of us at that time mobile
phones were not commodity Islam not
available so it was really a remote
setting or we spent the entire day
and the Knights discussing patterns
discussing other things about software
discussing projects and having fun and I
thought this idea is worth to be reused
and adapted to repeat to a European
setting and I started working on the
idea of setting up a European conference
on patterns that took me two years and
the more difficult part was to get a
slot in close the SS schedule they're
pretty much booked for the entire year
and space for 65 people was not easy to
acquire or to assign so it took more
than a year just to get in so because we
were just out the past I know that you
attended the first hillside meeting and
you we once talked about some anecdotes
that you experienced during that meeting
no it's not quite true I didn't attend
the very first hillside meeting that was
two or three years before I joined that
cabal my first exposure to hillside was
in 1994 at the opie conference in Munich
where I met Jim Killeen and showed him
what we did in our pattern work at that
time he was quite surprised to see that
somebody had Siemens or somebody Europe
was actually working on the subject as
well in addition to himself Gang of Four
and others so he introduced me to come
back who was also at the conference
talking about CRC cards and we met at a
bar in the evening Joe Kent our pattern
works and both invited me the next day
and to join hillside so I attended the
first hillside meeting I think it was in
1994 and that was at a hillside
no no that's that the first meeting the
first meeting of hillside was at on a
day at hillside the first meeting was
held in Colorado in Grady bujji's house
and he lives in the mountains so that
was the first hillside meeting and there
the name comes from
so what influence did the patterns have
over the past ten years let's say how
did they change the software development
community the best practices I think it
was a kind of revolution when the Gang
of Four book was in production or we
worked on patterns in the early 90s it
was a kind of eye-opener to us all of us
language of vocabulary to express design
ideas to the point with all the pros and
cons with the liabilities with benefits
the solutions the forces or what we
think is common sense today was
absolutely new in the early 90s we could
talk about design we could assess design
and we could inform our activities what
do we do here to address this or that
problem we had an expression for
requirements an expression to transform
requirements into working solutions and
that I think is commodity without
patterns I don't think any successful
software development is possible at all
there are common sense and the enormous
success of all the pattern books in this
world is a documentation of that success
still the Gang of Four book is
considered the most successful book on
software design in this world ever
Hausa one and poser two are considered
as among to be amongst the top five
books that has more had most influence
on the field of software architecture so
at one of the very first meetings on to
my first missiles I'm meeting we had the
idea of changing the world
the software world and looking back onto
what we achieved I think it it quite
became true
you mentioned architecting with patterns
this is it's a question that I often get
asked how to how do you really work with
patterns how do you architect with
patterns is there any guidance you could
give some brief sentences yes of course
there is some guidance important our
requirements the application you are
developing should always swing the baton
which means without quirements
that your solution must fulfill all
design work with or without pattern is
just guessing at best so start out with
the requirements if you have a specific
challenge to master such as keeping
coordinating a cooperating components
consistent or high-performance event
handling pick up and document the
concrete requirements speak forces you
expect from the solution to this
challenge or problem and then you can
match the concrete requirements of your
application against the forces of
corresponding patterns that address this
type of problem and if the force is
match well you have passed the first
step the second step is and that many
people actually forget this each pattern
comes with a cost
there is no free lunch so you should
look at the consequences specifically
that first of all the benefits
correspond to the forces and not
something different there may be
additional benefits but if the forces
are not resolved well then the pattern
is of no use and second to the
liabilities the potential drawbacks
sometimes they are not relevant for your
problem sometimes they are sometimes you
can afford the liabilities or drawbacks
and sometimes you can't if they you
can't afford them well you shouldn't
apply the pattern
yeah once you have reached that point
you can look at the concrete solution so
my the most important vice I can give is
look at requirements of your application
then look at the problem forces of the
pattern then look at the conference
consequences the good and the bad and
then you can work on the concrete
solution what roles does the pattern
introduce what cooperation between these
roles is happening and how do you
implement the thing rather than starting
with the solution in search of a problem
you start with a problem and work
towards the solution another important
guide suggestion I can give is there's
more than one solution to almost each
problem and for many problems and
software more than one pattern is
documented
there is no single iteration there is no
single state pattern there whole range
of patterns with different types of
problem and look on these are
alternatives the pattern the documented
pattern space of good patterns actually
consists of more than 2,000 patterns not
just 23 I've been asked a few times
about my opinion about anti patterns
what is your opinion about anti patterns
well this depends a whole lot of what
you mean by it if you mean the original
idea that Andy Koenig brought up I'm
with you I'll the idea is in this case
that you outline and describe commonly
applied solutions that do not do the
resolve the problems that intend to
address and discuss why they don't do
this and then lead on to the solutions
that work this is an important vehicle
for learning learning through failure is
an important vehicle to become an expert
and that we are missing this idea in
in software so this is nd conics
perspective on to this but what has been
made about of that concept in other
works that are more commonly known as
anti patterns I don't subscribe to that
because often though there I discuss
solutions as anti patterns which are
partly anti patterns which are partly no
patterns at all and the solutions they
suggests also examples of anti patterns
nevertheless whether something is good
or bad or a pattern or an anti pattern
also depends on the context for instance
if you use iterator to iterate of a
collection where the client is here and
the collection is remote and using
iterator is the worst idea you can do so
you have batch iterators or enumeration
methods instead so it also depends very
much on the concept and Christophe
Alexandre actually is cusses this in his
work he distinguishes good and bad
patterns where bad patterns are
similarly - - what and iconic describes
his anti patterns in our current work on
on the conceptual foundations of
patterns that I'm that we are doing
together with Kathleen Haney and touch
made we also address the notion of
dysfunctional patterns and dysfunctional
pattern languages so things that are
patterns but don't work in the given
context to address the problem and
resolve the forces well but nevertheless
they are patterns because they're
recurringly applied and seen in the
world of software hmm so tell us some
more about the conceptual foundations
that you are working on yes I said
together with doc Schmidt and Kathleen
honey I'm working on the fifth volume of
the poster series which is called on
patterns and pattern languages and there
we reflect and revisit the original
conceptual works on patterns adjust them
according to hindsight and growth
growing knowledge about patterns and
also explore pattern languages and the
space between the dance which is from
complementary patterns so alternatives
to be given problem or patterns that
often show up together in combination
we have pattern sequences we have
compound patterns we take a semiotic
perspective on two patterns also
consider the organization of patterns
under problem frames which is a notion
that my Michael Jackson brought up the
famous Michael Jackson from the software
community are not that fancy guy give us
some examples for example for those
symmetrical patterns yeah for instance
if you consider pattern complements just
to give an example command often comes
together with the command processor so
these are patterns in combination they
complement one another in other
situations you have patterns in
competition such as builder and abstract
Factory you did you either the one or
the other but not both together so we
have a discussion about this specific
patterns opens a solution space for a
given problem but it's only one specific
solution to that problem whereas pattern
complements can help you to open a
broader discussion about the problem and
the solution space so the problem of
object creation and disposal is spawned
by all patterns that have you creating
things like as builder abstract Factory
a factory method prototype disposal
method and so on and having all these
patterns together help you to address
your problem attend much better
general than having only one solution at
hand so this about patent compliments
then we have patent compounds which is a
notion originally known as composite
patterns which is an overload of the
term John free seed is shaped in this
notion so we think to him
we have we know about patent compounds
or patent compliments as it was called
in the past this is similar to something
to a group of patterns that are a time
and again combined in a very specific
arrangement so it's not just that two or
three patterns show up together time and
again but also their specific
combination for instance you can
consider the combination of observer of
composite and others in a
model-view-controller arrangement they
show up there and also in the same
configuration which allows you to argue
is more of you control and pattern in
its own right or a patterned compound
well and depending on your perspective
you can argue for either position
bureaucracy is a famous example for
patent compound project really in 1998
documented arrangement of composite
chain of responsibility observer and
mediator to describe object hierarchies
where events can be passed up and down
higher crease and across hierarchies and
these patterns always show up in the
same arrangement in many many designs so
this is about compound patterns the next
thing is pattern sequences which is a
hype topic hot topic in the pattern
right now pattern sequence actually
describe a series of pattern
that if applied in the given order
create a system or system part or
address a specific subject in your
application or organization or whatever
is your target thing typically each
pattern resolves one specific problem in
isolation a pattern sequence lines are
patterns to help resolving a broader
thing such as designing a component
let's say that manages a network
topology or a communication middleware
how to design an orb can be designed
described in terms of a sequence of
patterns that are applied one after the
other and there's a whole theory behind
this that actually dates back or goes
back and has its roots in two Tony horse
book on communication on theory on heap
management traces and events that happen
there's a nice paper on that theory
available on the net yeah and then
problem frames Michael Jackson came up
with the idea of problems frames they
are rooted in the problem domain that
that things can be described with very
simple meaning for instance work piece a
trance transformation and there are
patterns that deal with this control and
patterns can address or can be assigned
to to specific problem frames and help
you thinking about them in terms of what
problems and what forces they are
dressing its what solutions they produce
and things like that so this is what we
are working on changing the topic a bit
from patterns to architecture what is
software architecture how would you
phrase it how is it different from
design I just asked you a few questions
to which you can then answer the stereo
principal difference in architecture for
enterprise and for embedded systems how
do you judge an architecture for its
quality and what what are your opinions
on those topics this is a whole range of
question the most important question is
what is software architecture well first
of all what is the difference to design
there is no difference in in true
English I learned design is the activity
and the architecture is not affect so
all architecture is design but not each
design work is an architecture there is
a famous quotation Soph the architecture
is about the important things so what is
it Grady Booch I think has the
characterization that I like most he
actually said the most important design
decisions define the architecture of the
system and most important is defined in
terms of cost of change so the more
costly the change of your design
decision is the more likely it has a
system-wide scope and therefore
addresses architecture and I like that
very much even though I don't know
whether it is the ultimate
characterization but what is most
important what drives you and what is
very expensive to change and that may
things like your distribution
infrastructure that may be things like
your transaction handling so what is
architecture for the one system may not
be architecture for another because it
is more tactical rather than strategic
and therefore expensive so is there a
principle difference between embedded
and enterprise systems and architecture
interestingly I think they share
whole set of properties put a different
edges of the same dimensions because
even in an enterprise level system
service-oriented which is from a frog's
eye view quite different - and that it
software there are common constrains and
current requirements you have very
limited memory friends are for instance
an embedded system but consider a source
system like Amazon has you can throw you
cannot always throw more hardware
against the software and then such a
large enterprise the system several gigs
of main memory is a very limited
resource a hundred processors is not
much
so you interestingly enough you apply
the same principles as the embedded
system development requires and the
sewer level at the enterprise level
again because when you google or go to
Amazon's website you expect quality of
service but they don't have infinite
hardware and resources at their side
total cost of ownership drives them like
others so my observation is that though
there are significant differences in the
types of technologies you are using for
instance loose coupling configuration
you have more resources but in the end
common principles apply for the same and
for both types of system what about the
quality how do you measure how do you
judge the quality of software
architectures a system is I think of
high quality if it meets the business
for which is it it is intended if it
meets its requirements if the
requirements complement the business
case then it is successful it should
fulfill the requirements
but no more it should be good enough we
don't want the best configurability but
the configurability that is just good
enough to fulfill the requirements in
the business case for the system we want
not the ultimate performance but exactly
that performance that is necessary if
you target for more than you create
design pearls that are beautiful and
brilliant by themselves but which are
over kills for the systems a system must
be good to fulfill its requirements and
meet the business case no more
how would you enforce and manage an
architecture in the large for a large
distributor team for example I wouldn't
I
actually don't recommend to work in a
distributed fashion
well there may be projects where this is
a organization form suitable to
implement stable architecture when more
and more features are added but to get
the original vision of the architecture
elaborate this vision towards a stable
architecture I don't think that
distributed development is successful in
this case I'll encourage project teams
to to ensuring to draw together the
experts to a common place as a small
team I've learnt my lesson on C++
Standards Committee what design by
committee means to set up a non
successful software project with a
sustainable architecture
it doesn't require hundreds of
developers from many many countries a
small team with key experts in their
field with domain experts with software
experts with project management experts
with testing experts can achieve more in
that case and I think
such a small setup in the beginning and
the bidding beginning of a system could
be a year for instance for a platform is
actually more the more important the
most to teach it your system is I've
learned that even when setting up a
platform something that that which whose
intent is to support a whole range of
gens even different product families we
the small of the team the better you
don't want to be everybody's friend then
you end up with a jack of all trades and
a master of none
you need to scope yourself you need to
take decisions and the more people talk
and discuss the less you're taking
decisions so basically what you suggest
is always have one key person one that's
called chief architect or one lead
architect and the other is contributing
but one person making the final decision
well not necessarily one person perhaps
a team but nevertheless there should be
in case of discussion in case of
different opinion there should be one
person having the final vote yes I know
that you are involved currently in an
Siemens wide education program for
software engineering
so then what makes a good Software
Architect are there many things the most
important skill I think is communication
an architect who is not able to
communicate is no architect and I don't
mean communication to developers this is
part of it but communication to all
stakeholders so in terms of business you
need to community you need to listen to
your customers or product management to
learn about the business case ask
corresponding questions of clarification
regarding requirements you need to
communicate your architecture to
Aster's you need to talk them to your
head of development you need to
communicate it to developers so all
these persons have their stakes in the
architecture but the stakes are
different and if you can communicate the
architecture in their languages you are
lost the other important area where
communication is essential is the larger
the team the more it is you can't do
your canoe all the work by yourself it
is often better to to identify where in
your system specific problems occur our
challenges are addressed and who the
people are and specifically in a large
software project where people are
working in teams it can happen that
different teams are working on the same
problems and resolve them differently
which creates a patchwork like design
that is hard to understand as an
architect you should go around and
discover those places but instead of
doing all decisions by yourself
bring those people together and enable
them and empower them to decide for you
and you just mentor them and coach them
so that the system-wide aspects are not
not forgot so communication bringing the
right people together when designing a
system when implementing it observing
what the team is doing is an important
capability and skill of an architect
you must it is not always you need to be
good in at least one or two areas and
you need to know about many topics to
ultimately decide about things but I
think it is more important to let your
people do the work the architecture is
shaped what it is designed to later on
implemented and what people program has
an impact on the architecture ultimately
the architectures in the code are not in
the paper and enabling the people to
work together bringing them together I
think is the most important skill and
that also relates to communication how
can people become successful software
architects I just can quote my mentor
Tristan I got here let them work on
difficult problems so do not start
teaching software engineering of
architecture by using small examples you
can resolve them in any technology and
you as a student or novice do not see
the benefits of those approaches so if
you put if you work on harder problems
which are difficult to resolve then you
may appreciate the different benefits
and contributions of the various
technologies and the other thing is
practice practice practice and practice
I consider software engineering not as
an engineering discipline and not even
at a art but as a craft and to buffman
requires years of practical experience
discussion with other craftsmen and the
manger I think those were already great
sentences to close this episode anything
final Frank to say well if you are in
the field of software development I
think what is most important in today's
fast running worlds of upcoming
technologies go back to the roots look
on the works of the old masters and you
will find how much things refreshingly
refreshingly new things you will find
there and work with that because this is
technology even if it is old that has
been proven to work that proved its its
feasibility and practicability for
decade decades and
they will-they these technologies will
help you to build successful systems
even today and then you can decorate
these all practices with more modern
technology even what is now known as
service-oriented architecture is common
wisdom of how to build components that
is more than 10-15 years old but it's
sold as new likewise what is known as
model driven software development today
has been practiced for more than two
decades in certain fields of embedded
software and we can better learn from
those practices rather than from some
people's yeah advocating these
technologies as brand new great thank
you Frank
thank you very much bye-bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se
- radio dotnet although we prefer
entries in our comment system on the
website so other people can see what you
think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details
[Music]
you